上帝之城
City of god
该死  那只鸡跑了  快追啊  伙计们
Fuck, the chicken's got away! go after that chicken, man!
快点  该死的
Go on, for fuck's sake!
抓住那只鸡
Get that chicken!
如果拍张好照片  我就能在报社找到工作
If it's a good photo, I'll get a job at the paper.
-你这么想  芝麻菜  -值得一试
- You think so, Rocket? - Gotta take the risk.
你为了一张照片就不要命吗  算了吧
You'd risk your life for a picture? forget it!
你以为我想看见那些混蛋
You think I want to meet up with that motherfucking hood?
抓住那只鸡  老兄
Get that chicken, bro!
混蛋  我叫你抓住那只鸡
Motherfucker! I told you to grab that chicken!
滚开
Out of my way!
抓住那只鸡
Get that chicken!
如果里尔泽抓住你  会杀了你的
If Li'l ze  catches you, he'll kill you.
是啊  他得先找到我再说
Yeah, well, he's gotta find me first.
小孩  抓住那只鸡  抓住它
Hey, kid! get that chicken! get that chicken!
该死  警察
Shit! the cops!
别他妈逃跑
Don't fucking run off!
给我枪
Give me that.
傻瓜  你真他妈碍事
Hey, melonhead! you fucking fag!
一张照片就可以改变我的一生  但是
A picture could change my life, but...
在上帝之城  如果你要逃跑  他们会抓你
In the city of god, if you run away, they get you...
-你不跑也会抓你  -他们是来抓我们的
- And if you stay, they get you too. - They’re coming for us!
小时候就是这样
It's been that way ever since I was a kid...
六十年代
The sixties
你真没用  伙计
You’re useless, man!
-把球捡回来  -废物一个
- Go get the ball! - Fucking useless!
孩子们
Hey, kid!
把球给我  我玩玩
Give me the ball, I wanna play.
-这不是你的  -你敢招惹我
- It's not yours. - You wanna mess with me?
滚开
Fuck off.
-你叫什么名字  -抱歉  忘记介绍我自己了
- What's your name? - Sorry, I forgot to introduce myself.
-我叫芝麻菜  -给你点建议  芝麻菜
- My name’s Rocket. - Some advice, Rocket...
不要让小傻子拿球  他球技很差
Don’t let li'l dice touch that ball. he sucks.
-抢到了  伙计  -快跑  三毛
- You lose, pal. - Go, Shaggy!
这就是三毛
That's Shaggy.
关于上帝之城的故事  我要从他开始讲起
To tell the story of the city of god, I have to start with him.
8, 9, 10, 11...
但是要讲三毛的故事
But in order to tell shaggy's story,
我就得先讲少年三人帮的故事
I must tell the story of the Tender Trio.
三毛  气罐车就要来了  你还在磨蹭什么
Well, Shaggy? the gas truck’s coming. what are you fucking around for?
是不是害怕了
You’re not gonna chicken out...
少年三人帮的故事
The story of the Tender Trio
臭名昭著的少年三人帮
The notorious Tender Trio
在上帝之城是个传奇
was legendary in the city of god.
三毛...
Shaggy...
剪刀...
Clipper...
还有阿呆
And Goose
小骰子和傻蛋总是尾随其后
Tagging along were always Li'l Dice and Benny...
他是三毛的弟弟
Shaggy's brother.
我从来都不敢跟着我的哥哥  阿呆
I never had the courage to follow my brother, Goose.
好  我们走
Okay, let's go.
快点  阿呆
Come on, Goose.
我们上
Let's go!
停下  停下  该死的停下
Stop! stop! stop this fucker!
停下  不然我就开枪了  混蛋
Stop or I'll shoot, motherfucker!
滚出来
Get out!
快点  蠢猪  交出钱来
Hurry up, asshole! gimme the money!
谁要煤气
Who wants gas?
再掏  为了老板的钱  你不要命了吗
More! You wanna die for your boss damn money?
这里有好多钱
Shitloads of money here!
看到了吗  蠢猪
You see, asshole?
蠢猪
Asshole!
该死  警察来了
Fuck! the cops!
快跑
Let's get out of here!
快跑  这里全是警察
Clear out! the place is crawling with cops!
-三毛  -接球  阿呆
- Shaggy! - The ball, Goose, it's yours!
那时候  我认为少年三人帮的那些人
Back then, I thought the guys in the Tender Trio...
是里约热内卢最坏的家伙
Were the most dangerous hoods in Rio.
给  买些新球
Here! buy some new balls.
但是他们只是不成熟
But they were just amateurs.
连我的哥哥阿呆也是
Even my brother, Goose.
芝麻菜  把这些钱给爸爸
Rocket, give this money to dad.
但别说是我给的
But don't tell him it's from me.
好吗
Okay?
-线头  -怎么了
- Hey, Stringy! - Yeah?
看我有这么多钱
Look how much I've got.
我们来到上帝之城  希望这里是乐土
We came to the city of god hoping to find paradise.
由于洪水和贫民窟的纵火
Many families were homeless due to flooding...
很多家庭都流离失所
And acts of arson in the ghettos.
-一个电线杆  -我们要通电了
- A light post! - We'll have electricity!
政府领导人可不是开玩笑
The bigwigs in government didn't joke around.
无家可归  就去上帝之城
Homeless? off to city of god!
那里没有电  没有柏油路和交通工具
There was no electricity, paved streets or transportation.
但对有钱有势的人来说  我们的问题不重要
But for the rich and powerful our problems didn't matter.
这里和海报中的里约热内卢
We were too far removed...
差距太大了
From the picture postcard image of rio de janeiro.
你觉得将来我会成为救生员吗
Do you think I can become a lifeguard one day?
我不知道
I don’t know.
救生员总比卖鱼的好
Being a lifeguard is better than a fishmonger.
我不想卖鱼  太臭了
I don’t want to sell fish. it stinks.
-你在侮辱你爸爸吗  -没有
- Are you insulting your father? - No.
你将来想做什么
So what do you want to be?
我不知道
I don’t know.
-不做流氓也不做警察  -为什么
- Not a hood or a policeman. - Why not?
我怕被枪打死
I'm scared of getting shot.
把那个拿一边去  小破孩  你缺心眼啊
Put that thing away, kid. Are you nuts?
拿枪指着我
Pointing that gun at me?
没事的  阿呆  小骰子跟我来的
Take it easy with the kid, Goose. Li'l Dice is with me.
对  我也是个匪徒
Right, I'm a gangster too.
-抢燃气卡车赚得太少了  -那干啥
- That gas truck didn't bring much. - So what?
-我们每天都抢劫气罐车  -今天一个  明天一个
- We rob gas trucks every day. - One today, another tomorrow.
不  我们应该去抢些富人
No, we need to rob some rich guy's house.
那是唯一逃离这里的方法
That's the only way to get out of here.
该死  不要  你们只要按我的计划办就行
Hell, no. What you need is to follow my plan.
看看
That's it.
这小子开始不知道天高地厚了
The little fart's getting too big for his britches!
他抽多了  开始胡说八道
He gets high and starts talking bullshit.
你俩瘾君子连这孩子的一半都不如
You two junkies aren't worth half as much as that kid.
小骰子你有什么主意
What you got in mind, Li'l Dice?
想成为真正流氓光有枪是不够的  要有思想
To be a real hood you need more than just a gun. you need ideas.
小骰子就拥有这思想
And Li'l Dice had them.
-那是旅馆吗  -是
- Is that the motel? - Yeah.
我们进去抢钱就出来  别杀人  明白吗
We go in, grab the money and get out. No killing, got that?
-我要这把枪  -别动我的枪  臭小子
- I need this. - Don't touch my gun, kid.
再也不准动
Don't ever do that again.
-别指着我  -去你妈的
- Don't point at me. - Fuck you.
-别拿手指我  -别胡闹了
- Don't point your finger at me! - Stop acting like a baby!
这个给你
Here's yours.
-太棒了  -我们走
- Awesome! - Let’s go!
-别那么快  -怎么了
- Not so fast! - What?
你留在这儿  放哨
You stay here and keep watch.
如果警察来了  用枪打那个窗户
If the cops come, shoot that window over there.
-为什么我放哨  让那个傻瓜做  -听着
- Why me? Let that dork do that. - Look...
我免费给你提供计划
I gave you this great plan, for free...
而那个家伙纯粹废物一个
... while that guy's absolutely useless!
-是你的主意  -当然
- You just had the idea. - Exactly!
记住你还是个孩子
You're just a kid, remember?
你为我们放哨好吗
You cover us, okay?
会有机会的  所以不要了太心急
You'll get your turn, so cool it. stop trying to rush things.
你留在这儿
You stay there.
抢劫  婊子
This is a hold-up, bitch.
你应该学习或者工作  你看着就不像流氓
You should be studying or working. You don't even look like hoodlums.
所以  你应该工作或者学习  孩子
Instead, you ought to be working or studying, boy.
闭嘴  真烦人
Shut up! what a pain in the ass!
好了吗  剪刀
Okay, Clipper?
我们进去吗
Shall we go in?
我没叫东西
I didn't order anything.
免费给的  先生  拿出钱来
It's on the house, sir. Hand over the money!
冷静  我只要钱
Keep calm, all I want is your cash.
-别开枪  -你的钱包
- Don’t point that... - Your wallet...
老兄
Hey, man...
这是什么妓院啊
What kind of whorehouse is this?
-你是教堂的吗  -是的  兄弟
- You from the church? - Yes, brother.
给我
Give it to me!
荡妇
Slut!
你这又老又肥的家伙
You're old, fat and flabby!
想占她便宜吗
Wanna take her place?
怎么了
What's going on?
-警察来了  快撤  -快走
- The cops! let's beat it! - Let's go!
开那辆车  我去找小骰子
Take that car. I'll go get Li'l Dice.
天  真是辆好车
Jesus, what a car!
有点不对劲  小骰子不见了
Something fucked up. Li'l Dice's gone.
警察开枪了  快走吧
The cops are shooting, Let's go!
慢点  等一下
Slow down! hold on...
-你说过你会开车的  -我会  别紧张
- You said you knew how to drive. - I do, so cool it!
转弯  小心
Turn! watch out!
你个蠢猪
You fucking asshole!
我不是故意的
Hey, I didn't do it on purpose.
谁也没看见  闭上你的臭嘴  懂吗
No one saw anything. so keep your mouths shut, understand?
等一下  我脚扭了
Hold on, I twisted my ankle.
阿呆  看看他的脚
Goose fucked up his ankle.
疼死了
It fucking hurts.
带他进树林  我开枪调开警察
Take him into the woods. I'll shoot to distract the cops.
-上帝保佑  -上帝保佑
- In God we trust. - In God we trust.
给我电话  企鹅
Pass me the telephone, Penguin.
矮子是上帝之城另一个臭名远扬的家伙
Shorty is another notorious guy in the city of god.
但还没到讲他的故事的时候
But it's not yet time to tell his story.
-阿呆  真他妈疼死我了  -闭嘴
- It fucking hurts, goose. - Shut up.
-等等  -你像个女孩似的  活计
- Wait up... - You sound like a damn sissy, man.
-伸手  爬上来  -没人看见
- Give me your hand! climb up! - No one saw anything?
真奇怪  一辆车撞进酒吧  没有人看见
How odd! A car crashes into a bar and no one saw a thing.
你们真的什么也没看见吗
I suppose you didn’t see anything either?
和以前一样  没人看见  没人知道
As usual, no one saw, no one knows.
怎么了  矮子
So what's up, Shorty?
他们藏在树林里
They're hiding in the woods.
-你好  傻瓜  -你好吗
- Hello, melonhead. - How are you doing?
我感觉他们已经逃进树林了
I have this feeling that they're out in the woods.
-该死的混蛋  -他们逃进树林里
- The motherfuckers. - They’re out in the woods.
飞利浦  检查一下车  兰热尔  跟我走
Felipe, lock up the car. Rangel, come with me.
我什么也看不见  他们怎么能看见
I can't see a thing. How the hell can they see?
该死的树林
Fucking jungle.
-他们在旅馆抢劫了  -我知道
- They stole a fortune at that motel. - I know.
如果我们找到钱怎么办
What if we took the money?
你疯了  我不想掺和
Are you crazy? I'm not getting mixed up in that.
我想消灭这些家伙
I want to exterminate these guys.
为什么  从黑人和罪犯那里偷钱也是犯罪吗
What? since when is stealing from niggers and thieves a crime?
逮住他们并不困难  我在上帝之城有个线人
It won't be hard to nab them. I have a stoolie in the city.
-你听见那些枪声了吗  -我抓住一个就杀一个
- Did you hear those shots? - If I catch one of them, I'll kill him.
马拉卡纳
Maracana!
开门
Open the door.
-怎么了  -条子追我
- What's the matter? - The cops are after me.
三毛
Shaggy!
-三毛  -警察追上来了
- Shaggy! - The cops are on my ass!
-让我躲一躲  -快  进来
- Hide me! - Quick, come in.
该死  我以为警察会一晚上都呆在那里
Shit... I thought the cops would be down there all night.
我有理想  阿呆
I had a vision, Goose.
你抽了啥了
You been smoking something?
-你有工作对不对  -是的
- You've had a job, right? - Yeah.
什么工作  别人怎么看
What's it like? What do people say?
我给我爸工作
I worked with my father.
我爸说很多废话
And fathers talk a lot of shit.
知道吗  阿呆
You know what, Goose?
我想退出了  我不想死
I'm getting out, I don't want to die.
流氓的生活  不太适合我
This gangster’s life isn't for me.
等等  警察还在下面
Wait! the cops are still down there.
我不在乎
I don't give a shit.
我要回教堂了
I'm going back to the church.
他住在最高的隐蔽之处
He that dwells in the secret place of the most High...
拥有全能大显之力  我说的是耶和华
Shall abide under the shadow of the Almighty. I will say of the lord...
他是我的庇护神  避难所  相信上帝
He is my refuge and my fortress, in him will I trust.
你必不怕黑夜的惊骇  或白天的飞箭
Fear not the terror by night, nor the arrow that flies by day...
也不怕黑暗中的罪恶  不怕毁灭
Nor the pestilence that walks in darkness, nor the destruction...
-站住  混蛋  -别动
- Stop, motherfucker! - don't move!
站住  再跑我开枪了
Stop, or I'll shoot!
拥有全能大显之力
...shall abide under the shadow of the almighty.
在旅馆的抢劫平静下来
The hold-up at the motel went down
成为历史上最血腥的杀戮
as the bloodiest in history.
歹徒们命运却不同
The destinies of the outlaws then took different paths.
我觉得这家伙不是抢劫犯
I don't think this guy was involved in the heist.
看看这
See here?
-他是个工人不是流氓  -我现在把他变成流氓
- He's a worker, not a hoodlum. - I'll make him one now.
命运将剪刀带回上帝的手里
Destiny put Clipper back into the hands of god.
三毛在波妮丝的手里
Shaggy was in Bernice's hands.
阿呆在爸爸手里
And Goose was in my father's hands.
你为什么要那样  你以为我傻吗
Why do you do these things? you think I'm a fool?
从现在开始  你要给我干活儿
From now on, you'll work with me.
你弟弟会看着你
Your younger brother will keep an eye on you.
听着
You listen to me.
如果我发现你有歪财  我就杀了你
If I catch you with money that isn't yours, I'll kill you.
你也一样  换衣服  马上去工作
That goes for you too. get changed! you start work immediately.
有个流氓哥哥很糟糕  永远都是你买单
Having a hood as a brother sucks. you always end up footing the bill.
不要担心  爸爸是生我的气
Don't worry. dad's mad at me...
但很快就没事的
But he'll get over it.
给我  芝麻菜  这不是你干的  你要学习
Give me that, Rocket. it's not for you. you have to study.
-中枪你也不害怕吗  -我是流氓因为我很笨
- Getting shot doesn't scare you? -I'm a hood because I got no brain.
但是你很聪明  你应该好好学习
But you're smart. you should study.
我上学是因为我不喜欢体力劳动
I go to school because I don't like physical work.
向我保证  你永远不碰这枪  发誓
Promise me something... that you'll never touch this gun. promise?
握握手
Let's shake.
我们最好快点
We'd better hurry.
还有很多鱼要卖  别笑了
I'm gonna sell a lot of fish. and don't laugh.
我挨打的时候你笑了
You grinned when I got slapped.
-谁  我  -我看见了
- Who, me? - I saw you.
怎么了  三毛  猫咬你舌头了吗
What is it, Shaggy? Cat got your tongue?
你坐立不安的让我也很紧张
Your fidgeting behind me makes me nervous.
-我在想该怎么给你说  -你也会想吗
- I'm thinking of what to say to you. - You’re thinking, as well?
别想了  你不擅长思考
Don't. It'll be your downfall.
我的心有所属  那人就是你
My heart has chosen you. and I follow my heart.
你跟我开玩笑吗
Are you pulling my leg?
你没听说过一见钟情吗
You never heard of love at first sight?
流氓们不懂爱  只有欲望
Hoods don't love, they desire.
我只要说话你就反驳我
You cut down everything I say.
流氓们不聊天  他们只会花言巧语
Hoods don't talk, they smooth-talk.
算了  我还是别浪费口舌了
Well, I'll stop wasting my breath on you.
流氓不会罢手  只会暂停
Hoods don't stop, they take a break.
跟你谈爱情确实很复杂
Talking to you about love sure is complicated.
这不是爱情  是骗局
It's not love, it's a con game.
只是  我爱你
It's just that I love you.
你还是别说服我了
You just might end up convincing me...
抢劫之后  警察们不断来贫民窟搜查
After the hold-up, there were constant police raids in the ghetto.
每天都有人进监狱  有人被逮捕
Every day, someone went to jail, someone was nailed.
但没人看见什么  也没人知道什么
But no one had seen anything. no one knew anything.
没人像警察告密说小偷藏在什么地方
No one blabbed to the cops about where the thieves were hiding out.
3个月后
3 months later
三毛
Shaggy...
为什么不改变一下你的生活
Why don't you change your life?
找个工作而不是整天躺在床上
Get a job instead of lying around in bed all day.
-无所事事  -你什么意思
- Good-for-nothing! - What do you mean?
你觉得工作可以挣钱  那就去啊
You think you can make money working? go ahead.
没错  三毛  我整天工作怎么你啦
That's right, Shaggy... What do you think I do all day?
别生气  亲爱的
Take it easy, baby...
你知道就是想和你在一起生孩子
you know all I want is to be with you, have kids...
有个农场  养鸡  种大麻  富裕起来
And a farm, raise chickens, grow pot and get high.
你的话对我来说就是花言巧语
Sure! for me, that's nothing but smooth-talk.
什么  我差点就因为那个旅馆发财了
What? I almost got rich with that motel job.
你开玩笑吧
Are you kidding?
警察们还在为旅馆的谋杀找你们
The cops are still looking for you because of the deaths in the motel.
谋杀  你说什么
What deaths? what are you talking about?
你看见啦  你知道个屁  闭嘴
Did you see anything? you don't know shit, so shut up.
你没在场  我一个人都没杀
You weren't there. I didn't kill anyone.
我打赌是那些警察杀的  让我来背黑锅
I bet it's those fucking policemen, and I'm the one taking the rap.
他们甚至逮捕了小骰子  所以别再提了
They even nabbed Li'l Dice. So don't bring it up again!
-我不管是谁杀的  -反正不是我
- I don't care who did it. - It wasn’t me.
我这么说吧  我不想孩子他爸是个流氓
Let me just say... I don't want my kid's father to be a hoodlum.
你现在是一个人了  三毛
You're all alone, Shaggy.
-一个人  -没错
- All alone? - That's right!
-剪刀信教了 -哈利路亚
- Clipper's gone religious. - Hallelujah!
-阿呆在工作 -马屁精
- Goose is working. - Ass-kisser!
-而你呢   -我没变  那又怎样?
- And you? - I haven't changed. So what?
是他们背弃我
They've deserted me, that’s all.
那我也要背弃你
Then I'm deserting you too.
我要离开这里  三毛  你要想的话我们一起走
I'm splitting, Shaggy. Come with me, if you want.
否则我自己走
Otherwise, I'll go alone.
卖鱼啦
Fish for sale!
我哥答应不再鬼混
My brother had promised to stop messing around.
但流氓从不罢休  只会暂停
But a hood doesn't stop, a hood takes a break.
阿呆搞上了矮子的老婆
Goose began messing around with Shorty's wife.
有鳟鱼  但为你这样的特别顾客
I have trout. But for special customers like you...
我准备了接吻鱼
I also have a kisser fish.
那是乌鱼
Hey, that's a mullet!
你老公会替你口交吗?
Doesn't your husband...go down on you?
不会
No.
我老公都会在进入之前帮我口交半小时
Mine, before entering me, has to use his tongue.
你有让他肛交吗
For about half an hour.And from behind? Do you let him?
-当然没有  不会痛吗 -前几次会
- Good God, no. Doesn't it hurt? - The first few times.
之后可爽了  不过得准备香蕉
Then you'll see, it's fantastic. But you need a banana.
干什么
What for?
你真不懂得享乐
You’re missing the good things in life, girl!
拿根香蕉  加热
You take a banana, warm it up...
他跟你肛交的时候  前面就塞香蕉
Put it up your thing, while he takes you from behind.
爽死了  问你老公这么干
It's a real rush!  Ask your husband.
不行  你不了解他  他八成会揍我
I couldn't. You don't know him. He's liable to beat me.
试试看  男人最爱这种花招
Try him. Men go wild for smut like that.
死黑鬼
Motherfucking nigger!
荡妇
Slut!
贱人
Whoring bitch!
芝麻菜  把短裤给我  快
Rocket, give me your shorts.Quick!
-快脱下来  -我才不要在大街上光屁股
- Take them off, dammit!  - I'm not going naked in the street.
你想看我死吗  快把短裤给我
You want your brother to die? Give me your shorts. Now!
你的衣服给我
Give me your shirt.
你的短裤  快点
Your shorts! Hurry up!
我就知道  每次我都得替他擦屁股
I knew it. It's always me who forks up for that bum.
那个混蛋跑了  那是他弟弟
The bastard ran off. That's his brother.
-那个小鬼  -我要阉了那家伙
- That brat there? - I'll castrate that fucker.
卖鱼啦
Fish! Fish for sale!
小孩儿  过来
Hey, kid, come over here.
-你哥呢  -他今天没上工
- Where's your brother?-He's not working today.
-是吗  上车  -我又没做坏事
- Oh yeah? Get in.- I didn't do anything.
-上车 -我的鱼咋办
- Get in! -What about my fish?
-快点  -我不想把鱼扔着
- Hurry it up, kid! - I don't want to lose my fish!
-别管鱼了 -坐下
- Forget your fish.- Sit your ass down.
-我爸会杀了我  -无所谓
-My father will kill me. - That doesn’t matter.
走吧  什么都没有
Let's go. There's nothing here.
那天  爸发誓再也不想见我哥
That day, my father swore he never wanted to see my brother again.
走吧  飞利浦
Let's go, Felipe.
而他也确实没见到  没人在贫民窟再见到他
And he never did. No one ever saw him in the ghetto again.
少年三人帮的故事即将结束
The story of the Tender Trio was coming to an end.
小骰子  妈的  我以为你在旅馆挂了
Li'l Dice? Shit, man. I thought you were a goner at the motel.
-你真他妈有钱  -别给他  傻蛋  那是我们的
-You're fucking loaded! -Don't, Benny. That's our money.
去你的  少废话  钱拿来
Fuck you. Cut the crap and give me the money.
傻蛋  告诉你个三毛  矮子告密了
Benny... Tell your brother Shaggy that Shorty is squealing.
-我要离开贫民区  -但矮子自顾不暇
- I'm leaving the ghetto. - But Shorty had his hands full...
线头  我们去看看
Let's go see, Stringy.
天亮前有邻居报警
A neighbor called the police before sunrise.
小报记者也跑来了
The tabloids went to town:
上帝之城的狠心丈夫活埋妻子
"Man Buries Wife Alive in the City of God"
除了记者  还来了一堆条子
Along with reporters, the place was swarming with cops.
流氓都跑了
The hoodlums took off.
-你找死啊  -如果你不听我的
- You wanna die? - It's you who's gonna die...
就是你找死  对这位女士客气点
if you don't do what I say. And show the lady more respect.
快开车
Let's go, dammit!
-前面有条子 -管他的  开车
- There are cops ahead. - Fuck them, let's go.
-去哪里  -随便  走就是了
- Where to? - Anywhere, just go.
-怎么搞的  -求你了
- What's the matter? -Have mercy!
-饶了我吧  这辆车很破  -少来  快发动
- This car's a piece of junk. - My ass! Start the damn thing!
得下去推车
It needs a push.
去推车  三毛
Push, Shaggy!
去啊
Push!
是你
You?
你想捉贼  在那边
You want to arrest the thieves? Over there...
捉住那个人
Nab that guy over there!
三毛  快点
Run, Shaggy!
停车
Stop the car!
-这边  他在那里  -抓住这狗娘养的了
- This way! He's over here. - We got that sonofabitch!
-他是凶手  -混蛋
- He's a murderer. - The bastard!
三毛死的那天  我记得很多人围观
On the day Shaggy died I remember the crowds...
还有人照相
and a camera.
我一直想要一台相机
I'd always wanted to have one.
去上学吧
Let's go to school.
-如何  -去海边吧
- Well? -Let's go to the beach.
但有考试
But we have an exam.
那又怎样
So what?
其他人都去了
Everyone else is at the beach.
走吧
Come on, let's go!
她穿比基尼了  但是不想去
She's in a bikini, but doesn't want to go.
你说这个干吗
What's that saying you have?
太阳是每个人的
The sun is for everyone.
海滩属于那些应该得到它的
The beach,for those who deserve it.
(70年代)
THE SEVENTIES
-看这边  -我16岁买了第一台相机
- Over here! - I bought my first camera...
我很穷  所以从等级最低
when I was 16. Like all poor people,I started at the bottom...
最便宜的机种买起
with the world's cheapest model.
芝麻菜  怎么样
So, Rocket? How are things going?
开荤了没
Any luck getting laid yet?
还没
Zilch.
-安洁莉卡  我为她疯狂  -芝麻菜  还没有进展
- Angelica. I was crazy about her.- So, Rocket, still clicking away?
她很漂亮  是我们这帮人里唯一有经验的
She was gorgeous and the only girl in our gang who screwed.
我想跟她做第一次
I wanted to lose my virginity with her.
跟她  伙计  她有男朋友
With her, buddy? She's got a guy.
-那又怎样  我又没吃醋  -她爸是军人
- So? I'm not jealous. -Her father's a sergeant.
人都有缺点  往中间靠
No one's perfect. Closer together!
我是这票朋友里的摄影师
I was the official photographer of our gang.
我们自称爵士人  大家都会付钱让我拍照片
The gang of groovies. Everyone paid to have copies of the pictures.
蒂亚戈  往后一点
Thiago, move back a little.
-这样行吗  -很好
- Is this okay? - Perfect.
我想抽大麻
I need a joint.
别抽了  现在流行吸白粉
Instead of smoking, man,  you should snort coke. It's far out.
你有在吸  蒂亚戈  我比较喜欢大麻
You snort, Thiago? I prefer a good toke.
你要想抽的话  我可以帮你弄到货
If you like, I can get it for you.
是吗  那就快去
You can? Then go on, move your ass!
但白粉才好  那是真正的醉麻剂
But the choice stuff is coke. That's a real nercotic.
是麻醉剂
Narcotic!
-你的嘴好咸  蒂亚戈  -去你的
- Your mouth is all salty, Thiago. - Screw you.
线头  你想当救生员
You want to be a lifeguard, Stringy?
-你从不下水 -我爸爸是救生员
- You're never in the water. - My dad's a lifeguard.
-赌一罐啤酒我比你游得好  -赌了
- I'll bet you a beer I swim better. - You're on.
如果你要  我可以去找黑仔弄一根大麻
If you like, I can go get you a joint at Blacky’s.
我愿意做任何事来取悦她
I'd have done anything to please her...
给她买大麻  白粉
Buy her pot, coke...
我可以去找大哥  用低价买到好货
I could go to the top dogs to buy quality stuff at a good price...
因为大哥黑仔是我的老同学
because the local boss was a former classmate: Blacky.
-谁  -芝麻菜
-Who is it?  -Rocket.
-最近咋样  -很好
- How are things down there? - Fine.
-其他人呢  -也很好
- And the kids? - Fine too.
-你想买还是抽  -买
- You want to buy or smoke a joint? - Buy.
进来  伙计
Come in, buddy.
是谁
Who is it?
这是黑仔的地盘
This was Blacky's turf.
但原本也不是他的
But it hadn't always been his.
-黑仔  -靠  小骰子啊
- Hey, Blacky.  - Fuck, Li'l Dice.
-来我这里还带人  -谁说这里是你的
- You show up like this at my place?  - Who said it was your place?
(这间公寓的故事)
THE STORY OF THE APARTMENT
齐利亚太太守寡之后开始贩毒
Dona Zelia began selling drugs here...
好养活她的女儿
when her husband died, in order to raise her daughters.
她会送毒品给为她服务的男孩
She also gave away drugs to boys at times in return for special favors.
她最喜欢大个儿  后来大个儿长大了
Her favorite was "Big Boy". One day, he grew very big!
齐利亚太外行  三两下就被取代
Zelia's operation was so amateur that he had no trouble seizing it from her.
大个儿利用青少年贩毒
Big Boy used the neighborhood kids as dealers.
-我那份大麻呢  -去你妈的
- What about my pot? - Stick it up your ass.
最会做生意的…
The best dealer...
是萝卜
...was Carrot.
-我可以喝一口吗  -喝吧
- Can I have a sip? - Sure.
他赢得大个儿的信任
He earned Big Boy's trust...
被升为经理
was promoted, and moved up to become a manager.
黑仔  我们20你5  好吧
Blacky, 20 for us and 5 for you, okay?
有一天萝卜的朋友跑来
One day a buddy of Carrot's showed up.
-他叫亚里斯多德  -我老婆要手术
- His name was Aristotle.  - My wife needs an operation.
他们家在萝卜落魄时收留他
His family had taken Carrot in when he was down and out.
兄弟有难  他不能不帮
He couldn't refuse to help a brother in need.
这是货  周五之前交钱
Here’s the dope. I want the dough no later than Friday.
-兄弟  你救了我一命  -周五交钱
- You've bailed me out, brother. - Friday.
他就像我的亲兄弟  大个儿
He's my buddy, practically my brother, Big Boy.
再给他一星期
Give him another week.
-你不杀他  我就杀你  -萝卜别无选择
- Either you kill him, or I'll kill you. - Carrot had no choice.
-我说了周五  -兄弟  别开枪
- I said Friday. - Don’t do it, man.
萝卜想杀了大个儿  不过不必
Carrot wanted to kill Big Boy, but it wasn't necessary.
大个儿没收买条子  死在狱中
Big Boy hadn't paid off the cops. He died in jail.
萝卜接收了大个儿的一切
Carrot took everything that belonged to Big Boy...
但房子他不要  不吉利
but didn't want the apartment...
他把它送给亲信黑仔
the place was ill-fated. Carrot gave it to his most trusted dealer...
-给你  150袋  -黑仔
- Here. 150 bags. - Blacky.
多给一点  这的毒品这么多
Give me more. This place is crawling with druggies.
于是他就这样接收了这个地盘
That's how he took over the local trade.
但为时并不久
But not for long...
谁
Who is it?
去看看
Go see.
-黑仔  -靠  小骰子
- Hey, Blacky. -Fuck, Li'l Dice.
-来我这里还带人  -谁说这里是你的
- You show up like this at my place? -Who said it was your place?
是啊  谁说的
Yeah, who?
-小骰子  怎么了  -去你的
-Something wrong, Li'l Dice?  -Li'l Dice, my ass.
什么小骰子  我现在叫里尔泽
My name is Li'l Z' now.
(里尔泽的故事)
THE STORY OF LI'L Z'
里尔泽从还叫小骰子的时候
Li'l Z' had always wanted to be boss of the City of God...
就想当上帝之城的老大
ever since he was little and was called "Li'l Dice".
他们爽了  不让我过瘾
They're having fun, and not me?
我想离开这
I want to get out of here.
干什么  你朋友抢过了  你还想怎样
What, kid? Your friend took  everything. What do you want?
那一晚  小骰子满足了杀人的渴望
That night, Li'l Dice satisfied his thirst to kill...
尽管他知道三毛不会放过他
though he knew Shaggy would never forgive him.
他离开上帝之城躲避惩罚
To avoid being punished he left the City of God.
辛苦工作赚钱
He had to work hard for peanuts.
-干得好  傻蛋  -小骰子和傻蛋混得不错
- Yeah, Benny! - Li'l Dice and Benny managed well.
他们有犯罪天份
They had the gift of crime.
-你拿得比我多  -我出的主意
- You have more money than me. - It was my idea.
他们只怕遇见大流氓
The only problem was running into an older hoodlum...
-像我哥阿呆  -小骰子
...like my brother, Goose. -Li'l Dice?
妈的  我以为你在旅馆挂了
Shit, man. I thought you were a goner at the motel.
你真他妈有钱
You're fucking loaded!
别给他  傻蛋  那是我们的
Don't, Benny. That's our money.
傻蛋  告诉你哥三毛
Benny, tell your brother Shaggy...
矮子告密了  我要离开贫民区
I'm leaving the ghetto. that Shorty is squealing.
阿呆
Goose!
这是三毛的  带着吧
From Shaggy. You'll need it.
小骰子在杀人的日子里长大
From one hit to the next, Li'l Dice grew up.
18岁就成了上帝之城里最受敬畏的混混
At 18, he was the most respected hood in the City of God.
你成年了  小心了
You're of age now, watch out!
和里约热内卢头号通缉犯之一
He was one of the most wanted robbers in Rio.
小骰子  你好吗
Li'l Dice, how's it going?
生日快乐  恭喜你成年
Happy birthday.  I'm so glad you've turned 18...
-滚开  -抱歉  朋友
- Get lost, Tuba! - Excuse me, amigo...
给我啤酒
Give me a beer!
混蛋  你没看到我吗
Didn't you see me, prick?
-对不起  活计  -你妈的
- Sorry, man.  - Up yours!
下次不会轻饶你的  混蛋
The next time, I'll waste you, asshole!
小骰子已经做好了准备
Li'l Dice was ready for anything.
我有话要说
I wanna talk.
-他急欲大展身手  -这儿哪几只羊最肥
- And he was itching to start.  - Who are the fattest cats here?
-一大堆  -你看杰瑞・阿德里亚尼
- There are tons of them. - Look at Jerry Adriani...
金链子  漂亮衣服
gold chain, snazzy clothes.
你看佩拉和他的妞
Look at Pereira and the chick he's with...
-贝妮丝  她跟过我哥  -你看他的车
- Bernice. She was my brother's girl. - Check out his car.
还有黑仔  金光闪闪
Then there's Blacky. Covered in gold.
金项链  金手表
Gold chain, gold watch...
你看萝卜和他的车
Look at Carrot, and his car.
-他们都是毒贩  -他们都很有钱
- They're all dealers. - They're all fucking loaded.
抢劫钱太少
Hold-ups bring in chickenshit.
-毒品才有赚头 -我懂了
- The big bucks are in drugs. - I see.
尤其是卖白粉
Especially in selling coke.
-但那要本钱  -不一定
- But you need money. - Not really...
直接杀了这些小丑接手他们的生意
We'll kill these clowns and take over their business.
-什么时候开始  -马上
- When do we start? - Now.
恶魔指点明路
Exu-the-Devil is the light that shines forth.
把你带来
He brought you here.
为何留在被上帝遗忘的上帝之城
Why remain in the City of God where God has forgotten you?
我知道你要什么  你想要力量
I know what you want. You want power.
我有东西可以让你如愿
I have something which will give it to you.
我把护身符送给你转运  孩子
To change your fate, I give you my protector, boy.
但你不能亵渎它
But you mustn't fornicate with the amulet...
否则你会死  另外
you'll die. otherwise...
你不再是小骰子  而是里尔泽
Li'l Dice... but Li'l Z'. The boy is no longer called
里尔泽会长大
Li'l Z' will grow up.
你追随我  我就保佑你
You stick with me, I'll stick with you.
小骰子就变成了里尔泽  大开杀戒
Li'l Dice became Li'l Z' and he began to kill.
某个早上  他抢了杰瑞・阿德里亚尼的生意
He started one morning, taking over Jerry Adriani's racket.
到了晚上  他几乎并吞了全城的生意
By that night, almost all of the rackets in the ghetto were his.
但是他没有动萝卜  因为萝卜是傻蛋的朋友
The only business he didn't touch was Carrot's...
只剩下这层公寓  不过好办
since he was a friend of Benny's. All that was left was the apartment... But that would be easy.
谁
Who is it?
-黑仔  -靠  是小骰子
-Hey, Blacky. -Fuck, Li'l Dice.
-来我这里还带人  -谁说这里是你的
- You show up like this at my place? - Who said it was your place?
-小骰子  怎么了  -去你的  什么小骰子
-Something wrong, Li'l Dice? -Li'l Dice, my ass.
-我现在叫里尔泽了  -他叫里尔泽  知道了吗
- My name is Li'l Z' now. - His name's Li'l Z', see?
-你完蛋了  -别杀他  他明白事理
- You're a goner, bastard. -Don't kill him. He understands.
对吧  黑仔
Right, Blacky?
都给你  我啥都不要  我不想惹麻烦
It's all yours, I don't want anything. I don't want no trouble, okay?
我应该趁机替我哥报仇
I should have taken this chance to avenge my brother's death.
饶你一命替我们工作  懂吗
You'll live, but you'll work for us. Understand?
但说得容易
That's easy to say...
-你要去哪里  -不关他的事  里尔泽
- Where are you going? -He's clean, Li'l Z'.
你叫什么  小屁孩儿
What's your name, kid?
-芝麻菜  -他是阿呆的弟弟
-Rocket. -He's Goose's brother.
-阿呆  -死掉的阿呆
-Goose? -The late Goose.
你走吧
Quick, kid. Run along.
告诉大家现在由我里尔泽当家
Tell everyone that this business now belongs to Li'l Z'.
我们会卖白粉  懂吗
And that we'll be selling coke. Got that?
可卡因
Cocaine.
-堂口在哪里  -前边  左侧
- Where's the turf? -Over there, on the left.
贩毒就像其他生意
Selling drugs is like any other business.
供应商提供货品
The supplier delivers the merchandise...
然后包装
which is then packaged on the premises.
在装配线上包装
It's done in an assembly line.
枯燥得很  大麻卷成一卷
Boring as hell... Pot is wrapped up in "lids".
可卡因则装成小包
Cocaine is put into packets...
十包或百包为一袋
and then into bundles of 10 or 100.
贩毒甚至可以当事业
You can even make a career in dealing drugs.
让小孩子去送货
The kids start out as delivery boys.
刚开始当跑腿传话的
They're paid to run errands and take messages.
然后再升为看风的  警察一来
Then they become lookouts. if the police arrive...
他们就把风筝放跑  大家撒腿就跑
the kites disappear and everyone scrams
再然后  就可以去卖货
Later, you become a dealer
或称之为蒸汽
or a "vapor".
温度一高  蒸汽立刻就不见
When the heat's on, the "vapor" quickly evaporates.
再往上升  就可以有枪了
Moving up the ladder, you have the "soldier".
要是数学好的话  还可以当管家
And if the guy is good at math, he can become a manager...
是老大的左膀右臂
The boss' right-hand man.
警察也从中得到好处  不找他们麻烦
The police receive their part and don't  make trouble.
自从里尔泽把他的对头都干光了
Since Li'l Z' killed off all of his enemies...
上帝之城就再也没有暴力事件了
There were no shoot-outs in the city of god.
你可以放心地开车去那里
You could drive there...
公子哥们在那儿买毒品都觉得很安全
The playboys felt safe buying their drugs there.
吸毒的人纷纷前来  里尔泽捞了一大把钱
Tthe city teemed with addicts and Li'l Z' grew rich.
-这样行吗  -成交
- Is it okay? - It's a deal.
-我都不知道该戴哪个了  -这个好
- I can't decide which to wear. - This one's cool.
要是贩毒合法的话
If dealing were legal,
里尔泽准是年度风云人物人物
Li'l Z' would have been man of the year.
但这对我来说却是个麻烦  我很怕他
But things were risky for me. I was afraid of him.
-而他却无处不在  -真他妈讨厌
- and he was everywhere. - What a drag this guy is.
每次想要大麻  我都得去找萝卜
Whenever I wanted to smoke a joint I had to go see Carrot.
半包  谢谢
Half a lid. Thanks.
不过这也值
But it was worth it.
因为我只跟安吉莉卡一块儿吸
I only smoked with Angelica.
她跟蒂亚戈分手了  我就上了
She and Thiago had split up, so I made my move.
-我本来快要追到她了  -这些照片真棒
- I was about to win her over... - These pictures are really great.
-真得吗  -我挺上相
- You think so? - I look good here.
-你在哪儿都好看  -我跟你说真的
- You look beautiful everywhere. - I'm serious.
我也是
Me too.
渐沉的夕阳  空寂的海滩  长长的吻
A setting sun, a deserted beach... a long kiss...
就是那种感觉
I was sure this was it...
可小混混们来了
But the runts arrived.
给我吸一口行吗
Can I have a toke?
给
Here.
我走了  再见
I'm going. See you later.
等等   安吉莉卡
Hold on, Angelica.
-你的烟  -给你了
- Your joint, man. - Keep it.
真酷
What a cool guy.
那是我第一次跟小混混们接触
That was my first run in with the runts.
牛排薯条  傻蛋
Steak and fries, Benny.
太好了  给
great! here...
-你的小费  -真的  谢谢
- A tip for you. - Really? thanks.
-你吃吗  -不用了
- Wanna eat something? - No.
-这表要吗  -安吉莉卡跟他分手后
- Wanna trade this watch? - After Angelica left him...
蒂亚戈吸得越来越厉害了
Thiago began snorting more and more.
-你爷爷的  -不是  我爸爸的
- Is it your grandfather's? - No, my dad's.
一旦吸毒成瘾  你就栽倒毒贩子手里了
When a guy is really hooked he ends up in the hands of the dealer.
-两包十根的  -一包
- Two bags of ten. - One of ten.
-好吧  一包  -蒂亚戈却是个例外
- Okay, one bag. -For thiago, it was different.
-小心  -对不起  神父
- watch out! - Sorry, godfather.
神父  去你的  是我给你孩子施洗的吗
Godfather, my ass. Did I baptize your kids?
-对不起  -赶紧滚
- I'm sorry. - Now beat it.
黑仔  借我车子骑一下
Blacky, lend me your bike.
喂  赛一程
Hey, wanna race?
-去哪儿  -到公路
- Where to? - Up to the highway.
-行  -预备  开始
- Okay. - Ready? go!
-累了吧  -恩  你很快
- Pretty tough, wasn't it? -Yeah, you're good.
从哪儿买的运动鞋
Where'd you buy those sneakers?
-就在这附近  -T恤也是吗
- Not far from here. - The shirt, as well?
-不是  在住宅区买的  -好
- No, uptown. - Cool.
名牌的
It's a designer shirt.
我给你钱  你帮我买一件行吗
If I give you money can you buy me one?
短裤和T恤
Shorts and a shirt?
能买什么就买什么
Buy whatever you can.
-你穿几号  -你量量
- What size are you? - Measure me.
-用什么量  -靠  当然是用手啦
- With what, man? - Shit, with your hand.
穿几号鞋  转过身来
Shoe size? turn around.
-傻蛋  -买着啦
- Hey, Benny! - You got the digs?
-就买了条裤子  -还有呢
- Just one pair of pants? - No, there's more.
-喜欢吗  -喜欢
- You like it? -yeah.
还剩了些钱
There's some change.
-给你了  -好
- keep it. - Cool.
这是傻蛋
This is Benny.
-这是  -嗨  我认识他
- This is Rocket. -hi. I know him.
我也成阔少了
I've become a playboy.
大家听着啊
Hey, gangsters, listen to this...
要小心
Watch out...
少爷们下蛋之前都要扭屁股的
Groovies shake their asses before laying a big one.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
滚  你们这群混蛋
Fuck off, you bastards!
笑话我
Making fun of me?
妈的
Asshole!
傻蛋  我不是跟你说过干掉萝卜吗
Benny, didn't I tell you to shoot Carrot?
他在这儿是个祸害
He's endangering the ghetto.
别发火  去跟他谈谈
cool it. Go talk to him.
我要杀了那混蛋
I'm gonna kill that fucker.
别再整天想着把所有人都干掉了
Stop trying to wipe out everyone.
我一定要杀了他
I'm gonna kill him.
别怕  安吉莉卡  这里的人很不错
Don't worry, Angelica. the guys in here are cool.
当然了  我才不怕
Sure, I'm  not worried.
你要去跳舞  傻蛋  萝卜呢
You gonna dance, Benny? what about carrot?
去吧  哥们儿  跟他谈谈
Go on, buddy. go talk to the guy.
傻蛋是上帝之城最酷的流氓
Benny was the coolest hood in the city of god.
他给人烟抽   喝酒也付钱
He gave away pot, paid for drinks.
里尔泽则正好相反  他有野心
Li'l Z' was the opposite. He had one obsession:
要当贫民窟的老大
To be the boss of the ghetto.
他想找茬抢过萝卜的生意
He wanted an excuse to take over carrot's racket.
-萝卜  -什么事
- Hey, carrot. - What's up?
你不该让那些小痞子去抢劫
You shouldn't  let the runts do hold-ups in the ghetto.
我们井水不犯河水
You look after your section, I'll  look after mine.
听清楚了吗  我去喝一杯
Got that? I'm gonna get a drink.
-芝麻菜  你怎么样   -很好
- Hey, Rocket! how's it going? - Great.
-嗨  傻蛋  -还好吗
- Hey, Benny! - how's it going?
-蒂亚戈  还好吗  -不错
- Hey, Thiago. how are you? - Good.
-我去一下可以吗  -当然
- May i? - Sure...
跳个舞好吗
Wanna dance?
-去你家行吗  -没问题
- Is it okay at your place? - No problem.
我爸妈不在  你可以一直跟她单独相处
My parents are out. you'll  be all alone with her.
-今晚你就可以告别处男了  -小点声
- You can lose your virginity tonight. - Not so loud, man!
大家都会听见的
Everyone will hear.
-你真漂亮  -谢谢
- You're beautiful. - Thank you.
-妈的  -没戏了
- Shit! - Nothing's happening.
我知道那些小混混是跟你混的
Look, man, I know the runts are associated with you.
当我是白痴吗  小子
Think I'm a sucker, you little brat?
想抢我生意是不是
you want to take my racket?
我是想跟你谈谈  你他妈太蠢了
I want to talk to you because you’re fucking useless.
放开
Get your hand away!
那帮小痞子会给我们惹麻烦的
The runts are screwing up our security, man.
把奶瓶给他
Give the baby his bottle.
萝卜  让那帮混混老实点  好吗
Carrot, just ask the kids to cool it, okay?
萝卜是个白痴
Carrot's useless.
他竟然让那帮小混混在他的地盘上抢东西
he lets the runts do hold-ups in his section.
这会把警察招来  影响生意
The police come around and that's bad for business.
好吧  我让他们停手  因为我喜欢你
I'll do it only because I like you.
不过你得给那孩子换换尿布
But you need to change that baby's diapers.
我们看到底谁才是小孩
I'll show you who’s the baby...
告诉那帮混混不许在我的地盘上抢劫强奸
Tell the kids that in my ghetto no one robs or rapes!
怪不得你叫小Z呢
No wonder you're "Little"Z'?
那帮小混混不守规矩
The runts were kids who didn't respect the laws of the ghetto.
他们到人家里  到面包店里抢东西
They would mug residents, hold up bakeries...
在萝卜的地盘尤其猖獗
Especially in Carrot's section.
你们干什么
What are you doing?
-老是抢我的东西  -可他们并不知道
- You rob me all the time! - But they didn't know...
上帝之城现在有老大了
That the city had a boss now.
谢谢您选择我们
Thank you for choosing us
上帝之城比以前安全多了
The city had become much safer for residents.
几乎都没有抢劫了
There were hardly any hold-ups now.
去找里尔泽就行
You just had to go see Li'l Z'.
-我们走  -别伤害那些孩子
- Let' go. - Don't hurt the runts.
我不会碰他们的
I won't touch them.
-嗨  牛排  -你好啊  里尔泽
- Hi, Steak. -How's it going, Li'l Z'?
去走走吧  牛排
wanna take a walk, Steak?
和你吗  等等
with you? hold on...
妈妈  我跟朋友出去一下
Mom, I'm  going out with my friends.
那是我吃过的最好的鸡
That's the best chicken I ever ate.
-那个老家伙吓得要死  -可怜他吗
- The old guy was scared shitless. - Feeling sorry for him?
疯了吗
You're crazy, man!
我们去抢银行超市什么的吧
Why not stick up a bank or a supermarket?
那才几个钱  卖毒品才能挣大钱
peanuts. drugs are where it's at.
对  卖毒品
yeah, selling drugs.
可你得先当跑腿儿的
But you have to start out as a delivery boy.
你愿意当跑腿的吗
you wanna be a delivery boy?
忽悠人的  要升级需要很长时间
It's a rip off. It takes a long time to move up.
你得等着哪个老家伙被杀了才能得到提拔
You have to wait till an older guy gets killed to move up.
我可没那个耐心
I don't wanna wait till some guy croaks.
我要学里尔泽那手
I'm gonna do what Li'l Z' did.
把他们都灭了
I'm gonna wipe them all out.
在说我吗  小兔崽子  老大我在这呢
Talking about me, kid? the boss is here.
回来  兔崽子
Come back, you brat!
-这帮小子还挺快的  -跑得真快啊
- They're quick, those kids. - They run fast.
都走了  只剩下你了  还有吗
They're all gone except you. any others?
你来替那些跑了的抵罪
You're gonna pay for the ones that escaped.
自己选吧
You choose.
是打你的手呢  还是打脚
shall I shoot you in the hand or foot?
快选
Come on, choose!
手还是脚
Hand or foot?
选  快点
Choose, for fuck's sake!
-手  -打你的小手  对吗
- Hand. - The little hand, eh?
很好
Cool.
牛排薯条  让我们看看你的能耐
Hey, Steak'n'fries, let's see what you're made of.
选一个干掉
Choose and then kill one of them.
算了吧  我来
Leave it. I'll do it.
一边去  喇叭  让他来
Butt out, Tuba. This is for him.
来  牛排
Go on, Steak.
快  选一个崩了
Go on, choose one and shoot.
快  我可没时间等你
Come on, I haven't got all day.
崩一个
Kill one of them.
来  牛排  我很急的
Let’s go, Steak. I’m in a hurry.
我想看看你怎么样
I wanna see what you're made of.
干得好
Well done!
你做到了
You did it.
我们要你了  击个掌
You're one of us. give me five.
很好  牛排
very good, Steak.
起来  小畜生  滚回家去
Get up, brat. go back to your rat hole.
不许瘸着走
without limping!
告诉你那些小朋友们
Tell your buddies that
在里尔泽的地盘上不许抢东西
no one robs in Li'l Z's ghetto.
走  别瘸腿  听见没
Go now. and no limping, okay?
酷  里尔泽
Cool,  Li'l Z'.
里尔泽赢得了民心
While Li'l Z' was winning the respect of the residents...
而傻蛋则赢得了安吉莉卡的芳心
Benny was winning angelica's heart.
而我  依然是个处男
As for me, I was still a virgin,
没钱  没女友
single and broke.
我也没办法
I had no choice.
窘迫的生活
SUCKER’S LIFE
我只好去超市打工
I had to take a job in a supermarket.
每天工作很长时间就挣一点点钱
I worked long hours for chicken feed.
我希望老板解雇我
I wanted to be laid off...
那我就能用解雇金去买个相机了
So I could buy a camera with the severance pay.
可天不遂人愿
But things didn't work out that way.
-是海滩上那个人  -嗨  老兄
- It’s the guy on the beach. - Hey, bro!
-还抽那个吗  -对
- Still smoking good stuff? - Yeah.
那哥们儿太酷了
That guy's too cool.
小子  过来  把上衣掀起来
Hey, kid. come here. Lift up your shirt.
那帮小混混  给他们机会却不要
We give these ghetto kids a chance and they don't appreciate it.
-我的解雇金呢  -什么解雇金
- What about my severance pay? - What severance pay?
那个该死的经理认为我是他们的同伙
That fucking manager thought I was part of the gang.
你犯了大错  被解雇了  快滚
You're fired for serious misconduct. Get out. Immediately!
半分钱都没拿到
I didn't get a single cent.
这就好像上帝告诉我
It was like a message from God:
诚实赚不来钱的  笨蛋
""honesty doesn't pay, sucker?"
玩玩犯罪
Flirting with crime
车来得太晚了  我上班都晚了
The bus sure took a long time to come. I should already be at work.
靠  把枪藏起来  你白痴吗
Shit, hide that gun. are you nuts?
是阿呆的  坏了
It was Goose’s. It's broken anyway.
这也不能怨我们
It's not our fault,
公司跑这条线的车太少了
The company runs few buses on this line.
犯错的总是别人
It's never anyone's fault. It's always someone else's.
遭殃的可是我们这些工人  还罚我们的钱
But it's the workers who suffer. And then, they make us squeeze!
祝您晚上愉快  夫人
Have a nice evening, ma'am.
我认识那个男的
I know that guy.
他也是上帝之城的  会认出我们来的
He lives in the city. He'll recognize us.
所以呢
So?
我们抢钱的时候他就不会太注意了
He couldn't care less if we take his boss' money.
好吧  上
Okay. Let's go.
小子   你们是上帝之城的吧
Well, boys? aren’t you from the city of god?
对
Yeah.
你们只付一个人的钱就行
I'll let one of you through without paying.
你们得好好学习  离开贫民区
You should study so you can get out of the ghetto.
那儿太乱了
It's too full of cops and hoodlums.
-你上过学吗  -上过  我还当过兵
- Did you study? - I was in school and in the army.
我还是部队最棒的神枪手呢
I was the best marksman in my barracks.
不过退役后我只能做这样的工作了
This job was all I could find afterwards.
我还练空手道  要是有人雇我的话
But I do karate. if I'm hired somewhere...
我就会离开贫民区
I'll  leave the ghetto.
-那你打架吗  -我追求爱与和平
- Do you fight, then? - I'm for peace and love.
不过如果非打不可的话
But if I have to...
他并不知道他要非打不可了
He didn't know he would have to.
但还不是讲奈德的故事的时候
But not yet, it's not time to tell knockout ned's story.
-我们该下了  -走
- We should be going. - Let's go.
-再见  -谢谢
- Good bye. - Thanks.
再见
See you.
我下不去手  他那么好
I couldn't do it. He was such a cool guy.
没错  他是格尔森的哥哥
Yeah, totally. That's Gerson's brother.
回家吧
Let's go home.
那边只有一家面包店
There's nothing here except that bakery over there.
-怎么想  -不知道  这是抢劫
- What will you say? - I don't know. "this is a hold-up."
这是我的电话
Here's my number.
-你喜欢灵魂乐还是爵士乐派对  -灵魂乐
- You like soul or groovy parties? - Soul.
又没抢成
That one didn't work either.
柜台那女孩儿太骚了  还跟我调情
The counter girl was just too foxy. And she flirted with me.
给我打电话好吗
Will you call me?
真不忍心拿枪对着她  她太迷人了
I ccouldn't pull a gun on her, she was too sweet.
我也这么觉得
Yeah, I agree.
我迷路了  请问去巴拉怎么走
Eexcuse me. I'm lost. how do I get to barra?
-巴拉  -对
- To barra? - Yes.
圣保罗来的这家伙可要倒霉了
"Tough luck for this guy from sao paulo."
-我们也要去那儿呢  -真的假的
- In fact, we were going there. - You're kidding.
-你是救生员  -对
- You're a lifesaver. - That's right.
圣保罗人都比较白痴
Because no guy from sao paulo could ever be cool.
-尸体在这儿  -找到了  队长
- The body's over here. - We found it, chief.
法医
The forensic expert!
-不太好看吧  -说的对
- Not a pretty sight, eh? - You said it.
-这歌手不错  -你喜欢他
- What a great singer. - You like him?
-我喜欢音乐  你呢  -那你喜欢大麻吗
- I love music. what about you? - Tell me, do you also like pot?
不知道  没抽过
I can't say I've never tried it.
同类相吸
The devil recognizes his own.
-有纸吗  -好像有
- Do you have papers? - I think so.
我有
I have some.
我可是卷烟的好手
I'd  always been an ace at rolling a joint.
我要是哄女人也这么拿手的话
If I'd had the same skill with girls...
早就不是处男了
I'd never have lost so many chances to lose my virginity.
你真是圣保罗人的例外啊
For a sao paulo guy you're very cool.
谢谢夸奖  老兄
Thanks, bro.
用的什么凶器
What did they use?
棍子或石头  小孩儿呢
A club or a rock. and the child?
-没受伤  -谢天谢地
- Untouched. - Thank goodness.
-多长时间了  -大概四个小时
- How long ago? - About four hours.
-能拿走吗  -没问题
- Can we take it away? - Go ahead.
凶手肯定是上帝之城的
The murderer has to be from the city of god.
混蛋  妈的
You bastard! you motherfucker!
你非得在这儿杀你婊子吗
Did you have to kill your chick in the ghetto?
-到处都是条子  -饶了我吧  里尔泽
- The place is crawling with cops now! - Come on, Li'l Z'.
饶了你  去死吧
come on? fuck you!
我得给自己雪耻
I had to avenge my honor.
她家人已经向警局告发我了
Family's turned me in.
你不会有麻烦的
you won't have any problems.
你把条子都引来了  你死定了  混蛋
The cops are everywhere because of you. you're dead meat, asshole.
行了  里尔泽  对他的惩罚够了
Let up, Li'l Z'. You've punished him enough.
你知道规矩
You know the law.
谁敢在我的地盘上杀人  谁就得死
Anyone who kills in my ghetto has to die as an example.
那是他自己的事  里尔泽
That was his business, Li'l Z'
听好了  狗娘养的  滚出贫民区去
Listen, you sonofabitch, get outta the ghetto.
一点都不懂规矩
You showed no respect, understand?
傻蛋
You know what, benny?
你心太软了  养虎为患知道吗
You're  too nice. If you raise a snake, expect to get bitten.
他不值得
He wasn't worth shit.
-叛徒  -闭嘴  喇叭
- A dirty traitor. - Shut up, Tuba.
我要跟我女朋友出去走走
I'm going for a walk with my girl.
好  小心点   等风头过去了
Okay, be careful. when things calm down...
我们去找萝卜解决我们的问题  好吗
we'll get back to our business with carrot, okay?
你该找个女朋友了  里尔泽
You need a girlfriend, Li'l Z'
知道我在想什么吗  傻蛋
Know what I'm thinking, Benny?
我很性感
That I'm so sexy?
这没错
That too.
但我是想  我们该干什么
but I mean, you know what we could do?
-再做一次爱  -我说真的呢
- Make love again.. - I'm serious.
我们可以离开这里  暴力太恶心了
We could go away from here. This violence sucks.
去哪儿
Go where?
去个农场
To a farm.
我们根本就是嬉皮  不是吗
We're really hippies at heart, aren't we?
农场
A farm?
平静浪漫
Peace and love?
傻蛋的告别派对
Benny's farewell
傻蛋那么酷  不应该做流氓
Benny was just too cool to go on being a hoodlum.
他的告别派对把大家都聚在一起了
He succeeded in getting everybody together for his good-bye party.
黑帮分子
The gangs...
灵魂乐手
The soul crowd...
-教会的   -有一天  我也会加入教会
- The religious crowd... - One day, I'll go to church
桑巴舞者
The samba crowd...
爵士乐手
The groovy crowd...
里尔泽  一辈子都没跳过舞
And li'l z', who had never danced in his life.
想和我跳舞吗
Want to dance with me? want to dance with me?
-我听不到  -想跳舞吗
- I didn't hear. - Want to dance?
不了谢谢  我和别人一起来的
No, thank you, I'm with someone.
芝麻菜
Hey, rocket!
哥们  过来我有话和你说
Come, I want to talk to you, buddy.
-你不能和那个妞一起跑了  -为什么
- You can't just split with that chick. - why not?
我要去乡下了  抽大麻  听摇滚
I'm gonna go live on a farm, smoke pot, listen to rock.
你想为了个贱人把我们的事业抛之脑后
You wanna throw away everything we've accomplished for that bitch?
她不是贱人  她是我女人
She's not a bitch, she's my girl.
我们接管萝卜的生意  到时候都是你的
We'll take over Carrot's business, it'll be yours.
-放过萝卜把  他是个好人  -他就一王八蛋
- Leave carrot alone, he's a good guy. -he is a motherfucker!
谁对你来说都是王八蛋
See? everyone's a motherfucker to you.
这就是我为什么要离开
That's why I'm leaving.
你得理解  我必须走
You got to understand, I have to go.
我们情同手足  不过我受够了
I love you, man, but I've had enough.
妈的  让我看看你多有种
Motherfucker, let's see if you have any balls.
-什么  -你想死吗  滚开  贱人
- what is this? - You wanna die? fuck off, bitch!
快脱  黑鬼  我要看你屁股
Strip, nigger. I wanna see your ass.
快点  全脱掉
Hurry up! take it all off! now!
我要看你屁股  快点  蠢货
I wanna see your ass. come on, faggot!
来吧  黑鬼
Let's go, nigger!
给大家看看你的屁股
Show your ass to everyone!
求你了
Please...
-快他妈脱  -快点
- Strip, dammit! - Hurry it up!
傻蛋  这个相机换袋白粉  行不
What's up, benny? this camera for a bag of coke?
我已经洗手不干了
I don't deal anymore.
拜托  给点吧  咱们是朋友嘛
Come on, do it for me. you are my friend.
-是偷来的吧  -不是  我爸的
- Is it stolen? - It's okay, it's my dad's.
你爸的
Your dad's?
-送给里尔泽  -芝麻菜会喜欢的
- Give it to li'l z'? - Rocket would love this camera.
-给你  -太好了
- Yeah, here. - Great.
我来了
Here I am!
-你想当摄影师  -对
- You wanna be a photographer? - Yeah.
-给你个礼物  -靠  哥们  太棒啦
- Here's a present.- Shit, dude! this is great!
现在扭屁股
Now move your ass. shake it!
你可以拍些好照片
You'll take some great pictures.
把那个给我
Give me that.
-把相机还给我  -不给
- Give me back the camera! - ?o!
你怎么啦  你疯啦
What's your problem? are you craz?
傻蛋被他们杀了
They've killed benny!
操  叫救护车  哪个杂种干的
Fuck! call an ambulance! Where's the motherfucker who did it?
-傻蛋死了  -快叫医生
- Ze benny is dead. - No! call a doctor!
滚出去  贱人  都怪你
Get out of here, bitch! it's all your fault!
杂种
Motherfucker!
萝卜在哪儿
Where's carrot?
黑仔在这里
Blacky's here.
他有麻烦了
He's in trouble.
我完了
I'm fucked.
-为什么  -我完了
- Why? - I'm fucked.
你也玩完了  我杀了傻蛋
And you are too. I think I killed Benny.
里尔泽要你的地盘
Li'l z is coming to take your place.
我们可以抓住他  他在舞厅
We can get him, he's in the dance hall.
你杀了傻蛋
You killed Benny?
我没想杀他  我想杀的是里尔泽
I didn't mean to. he moved. I was aiming at li'l z?
行了  走吧
Come on, let's go.
黑仔
Blacky...
你杀了上帝之城最酷的人
You killed the coolest hood in the city of god.
我们去搞定里尔泽
Let's go get li'l z?
萝卜知道没了傻蛋
Carrot knew that without benny
除非奇迹出现才能挽救他的生意
only a miracle could save his business.
我们死定了
We're fucked, man.
除了上帝之城还有哪会发生这种奇迹
But what better place for a miracle to happen than in the city of god?
看谁来了  我的小心肝
Look who's here. my sugar babe.
-让开  -亲我一下
- Let me by. - Gimme a kiss, girl.
请让开  你也不照照镜子
Let me by, please. have you seen what you look like?
拜托  里尔泽
Come on, li'l z
亲爱的  一切都好吗
Hi, honey. everything okay, baby?
问题很简单  里尔泽太丑  帅内德很帅
The problem was simple. Li'l z' was ugly. knockout ned was handsome.
帅内德什么妞都能泡到
Knockout ned could get any girl.
里尔泽要么给钱要么用暴力
Li'l z' had to pay or use force
这是一场好帅哥和坏丑男之间的决斗
It was a duel between the handsome good guy... And the ugly bad guy.
-放开我  -享受点嘛
- Let me go! - Just enjoy it.
反抗也没用  你是我的了
There's no use fighting. You're mine now.
蠢货  你的妞还挺辣的
Hey, faggot, your broad's really hot!
我根本不能面对她
I can't even look her in the face now.
那混蛋怎么不杀了我
Why didn't that fucker kill me?
等等  我怎么没宰了那个杂种
Hold on... why didn't I kill that fucker?
我们回去
Let's go back.
-萝卜怎么办  -以后再找他
- What about carrot? -We'll get back to him.
你打算杀了他
You gonna kill him?
帅内德  你的妞是个荡妇  出来  混账
Knockout ned, your chick's a slut. come out, motherfucker!
-滚出来  孬种  -放松
- Come out, you loser! - Take it easy...
我要出去  让我出去
I'm going out. let me go.
格尔森  回来
Gerson! come back, son!
跟你无关小子  我们来找你哥的
This doesn't concern you, kid. we're here for your brother.
谈谈吧  我们来解决  我哥不爱惹是生非
Let's talk, we can work it out. my brother's a peaceful guy.
长得帅就不把我放在眼里吗  叫他出来
Is he too good-looking to come talk to me? call him.
他什么都没做
He hasn't done anything.
你知道我是谁吗
You know who I am?
-里尔泽  老兄   -他是里尔泽
- Li'l z? man. - He's li'l z?
叫那个杂种
Call that motherfucker!
快去
Go on, man.
消消气  我叫他
Calm down, I'll call him.
胳膊  我弄伤了胳膊  萝卜得等了
My arm! I hurt my arm. Carrot will have to wait.
那孬种自找的
That loser got what he deserved.
走吧
Let's go!
格尔森
Gerson...
那个混账杀了我弟
That bastard killed my brother.
我跟他没完
I can't let that go.
-要枪吗  -儿子啊
- Want a gun? - My son...
冷静点  妈妈
Calm down, mom.
妈
Please, mom...
包好点  猪头
Do it right, asshole.
只能这样
There's no other way.
我怎么会被那个孬种伤到呢
How'd I let that loser hit me?
靠  被戳了个洞
shit, that's some hole.
-我们就跟兄弟一样  -闭嘴
- It's as if we were brothers. - Shut up.
我们俩都被伤到手臂
Both of us hurt in the arm.
你被弟弟砍  我被哥哥枪打中
you by one brother, me the other.
我们要真是兄弟就搞笑了
It would be really funny if we were brothers.
帅内德挺厉害啊  不知从哪就冒出来了
That knockout ned's not bad, eh? he came out of nowhere.
闭嘴  喇叭  你真他妈有够烦
Shut up, tuba! you're a fucking pain!
似乎上帝之城突然间有了个英雄
It was as if the city of god had suddenly found a hero.
上帝保佑你孩子
God bless you, son.
那小子就是在找死
That kid was just asking to be killed.
好样的
Well done.
干得漂亮
You did a good job.
你最好去躲躲
You'd better go hide
我还以为帅内德要造反呢
I thought knockout ned would start a revolution here.
不过老天另有安排
But god had other plans.
牛排  毒贩子们都去哪了
Steak, where are all the dealers?
他们都躲起来了  里尔泽心情不好
They’re hiding. li'l z is in a bad mood.
把我们搞上瘾  他们自己却躲起来了
They get us hooked and then they go off and hide.
帮我个忙  去给我搞点白粉来
Do me a favor. go get some nose candy for me.
我试试
I'll try.
跟他们说是给蒂亚戈的  别给我断货
Tell them it's for thiago, to keep my buzz going.
牛排薯条  去告诉萝卜
Steak'n'fries, go to carrot's and tell him...
里尔泽说如果你干掉帅内德  他就放过你
Li'l z' says that if you kill knockout, he'll leave you alone.
帅内德  你听到了吗
Hey, knockout ned. did you hear that?
抓住那小子
Grab the kid!
你听到了吗  你要是不跟着我们  你就完了
You heard the boy? if you don't stick with us, you're dead.
我建议你加入我们  我们就是搭档了
I think you should join us. we'll be partners.
我不贩毒
Drugs aren't my thing.
这是我和他之间的事
This is just something between me and him.
那些人狗屁都不是
Those guys aren't worth shit.
他们对老大言听计从
They'll do anything for power.
就像那小子
Like that kid.
他们就是机器人  和这个瘪三一样
They're all robots, like this punk here.
你在想什么小子
What's in your head, kid?
难道你不觉得你毁了你自己吗
Can't you see you're wrecking your life...
跟着那个疯子和一群好战的蠢货
With that maniac and a bunch of trigger-happy fools?
你疯了吗  你还是个孩子
Are you crazy? you’re just a kid.
孩子  我抽大麻也吸毒
A kid? I smoke, snort...
我杀人越货  我是个男人
I've killed and robbed. I'm a man.
操  你屁也不懂
Shit, you have no idea!
他有他的帮派  你应该加入我们
He's attached to his gang. you should join up with us.
-我们应该宰了他吗  -牛排  我们得给你点颜色
- Shall we kill him? -Steak, we're going to grind you.
-我加入  -太棒了
- Okay, I accept. - Great!
告诉你老大  帅内德和萝卜现在是一伙了
Tell your boss that knockout ned and carrot are now in command.
不能滥杀无辜
No killing of innocent people.
我不能接受伤及无辜
I can't accept that, understand?
行  不滥杀无辜
Okay, no innocent people.
牛排搞砸了
Steak fucked up!
-有枪给我吗  -没有
- Have you a gun for me? - No...
我们可以从店里枪
But we can hold up a gun store.
那不是问题
That's no problem.
我什么也不想抢  我不是流氓
I don't want to hold up anything. i'm not a hoodlum.
这是我和他的私人恩怨
This is a personal affair between me and him, okay?
我不是流氓
I'm not a hoodlum.
他上了你的妞
He raped your chick...
他杀了叔叔和你弟弟  他拿枪扫射了你家
Killed your uncle and brother, gunned your house...
你也干掉了他的人
And you killed one of his guys.
你要不是流氓就走吧
If you're not a hood, then get out.
帅内德的故事
The story of knockout ned
抢劫
This is a hold-up!
-第一次  -手枪在哪儿
- the first time... - Where are the revolvers?
帅内德从萝卜的枪口下救了个店员
...knockout ned saved a salesclerk from being shot by carrot.
我说过不杀人
We said no killing!
那是规矩
That's the rule.
把老板叫来  拿钱
We want the boss money.
大家冷静  把收银机打开
everyone keep calm. open the cash register!
你想让我们走  我们也想
You want us to go? we do too.
所以动作快点
So hurry up!
-低头  -第二次
- Look at the ground! - The second time...
萝卜救了帅内德一命
Carrot saved knockout ned's life.
帅内德懂了什么规矩都有例外
Ned learned that there's an exception to every rule.
规则的例外
Exception to the rule.
-你是经理  -是
- Are you the manager? - Yes.
打劫  所有人都趴下
This is a hold-up. everyone on the ground!
趴下
On the ground!
把钱给我
Give me the money!
我说真的呢
I'm not kidding.
谁敢动我就毙了谁
The first person who moves is dead!
第三次  例外成了规矩
The third time, the exception becomes the rule.
萝卜和帅内德准备向里尔泽发起挑战了
Carrot and knockout ned prepared to face li'l z'.
萝卜为了保住他的生意
Carrot could protect his business.
帅内德
Knockout ned...
这个帮派里的神枪手想复仇
The best marksman in his battalion, wanted revenge.
先看意大利的  9毫米口径
First, the italians. this is a 9 mm.
-让我看看  -不错吧
- Let me see. - Not bad, eh?
-瞄准镜不准  -我算你便宜点
- The sight isn't well-aligned. - I'll give you a good price.
12毫米口径  叫"手炮"
The 12 mm, the "hand job".
知道为什么
See why?
伍兹冲锋枪  9毫米  以色列的
Aan uzi, 9 mm. it's israeli.
-大卫之行  -犹太的
- The star of david. - Jewish.
我要30-06弹步枪
I want a 30-06.
可以爽一把了
Now we can start having fun.
战斗开始了  让我们一起来祈祷
The war's on. Let's start with a prayer.
我们天堂里的主是我们神圣的名字
Our father who art in heaven hallowed be our name...
我们的愿望将实现
Our will be done...
愿你的旨意行在地上就如同行在天上
On earth as it is in heaven...
小混混们有枪但是射不准
Hoodlums have guns, but can't shoot.
帅内德一枪等于里尔泽那一派的10枪
One bullet from knockout ned was worth ten from li'l z's gang.
里尔泽气急败坏  奋起反击
li'l z' couldn't take it. he counter-attacked.
本来就很苦难的贫民区现在更如地狱一般
The ghetto had been a purgatory, now it was hell.
我决定离开  这就是我如何成为记者的
I decided to get out. That's how I became a reporter.
照片太棒了
Great photo!
我打赌是罗杰里奥・里斯拍的
I bet it's by rogerio reis.
我就说嘛
What did I tell you?
就像所有的专业人员一样
Like any pro...
我从最最底层开始做起
I started at the bottom, way down at the bottom.
甚至不知道等待我的会是什么
Without knowing what awaited me.
我以报社为家
Instead of going home I'd go over to the paper.
工作室里一个人是从上帝之城来的
A guy from the city of god worked in the lab.
看这个
Check this out.
在他的帮助下  我离梦想又近了一步
He helped me move closer to what I loved most in life.
-罗杰里奥  -你好吗  皮埃尔
- Hi, rogerio. - How are you, pierre?
这是芝麻菜  他是个摄影师
This is rocket. he's a photographer.
你好  芝麻菜
Hello, rocket.
-他是你的粉丝  -真的
- He's a fan of yours. - Really?
有品位  芝麻菜
You have good taste, rocket!
-我下班了  -再见
- Well, i'm done. i'm off. - See you.
他真酷
What a cool guy!
原本应该迅速的复仇行动
What should have been a swift revenge...
现在成了一场全面的战争
Turned into an all-out war.
上帝之城一分为二
The city of god was divided.
人们不能在两个阵营的领地之间走动
You couldn't go from one section to the other.
甚至不能探亲
Not even to visit a relative.
警察把每个贫民区的人都当做是混混
The cops considered anyone living in the ghetto a hoodlum.
人们已经习惯了越战般的生活
People got used to living in vietnam.
而且志愿来送死的人越来越多
And more and more volunteers kept signing up to die.
这小子
This kid...
-你想要什么  -一个萝卜那边的小子打我了
- What do you want? - A boy from carro's gang punched me.
这场战斗成了所有事情的借口
The war was an excuse for everything.
我被里尔泽一个手下踢了一脚
One of li'l z's soldiers kicked me.
这个你的  点22
Take this .22.
上了我姐的那个混蛋是萝卜那边的
The jerk who raped my sister is with carrot.
里尔泽把我家人从家里赶出去了
Li'l z evicted my family.
杀人很
Kill... be respected.
-我很会做生意  -行  开工吧
- I'm pretty good in business. - Okay, get to work.
-你要什么  -干掉杀我爸的人
- What do you want? - To get my father's murderer.
-你叫什么  -我叫奥托
- What's your name? - My name's otto.
什么情况
What's the matter?
-他是个工人  -但他想要支枪
- He's a worker. - But he wants a gun.
他连一个星期也待不了
He won't last a week.
一年之后  没人记得所有争端时如何开始的
A year later, no one remembered how it had all begun.
接招
Take that!
对他们双方来说
For both sides,
目标只是接管对方生意来买更多枪
the aim was to take over the enemy's business in order...
然后再接更多生意
To buy more guns and take over more businesses.
我抽大麻  吸毒  我杀人越货
I smoke, snort, i've killed and robbed.
我是个男人
I'm a man.
媒体开始关注  警方也必须开始调停
The media started taking an interest. the police had to intervene.
上帝之城的一个黑社会头目今天被捕
A gang leader, from the city of god, was arrested today.
曼纽尔・马查多  又称帅内德
Manuel machado, a.k.a. knockout ned...
被李儿子帮派打伤之后在医院接受治疗
Was hospitalized after being wounded by li'l z's gang.
我们的记者采访了他
Our reporter interviewed him.
-争斗还在继续吗  -还在继续
- Is the war still going on? - It's still going on.
-死了很多人吗  -很多
- Have many people died? - Many have died.
大部分是无辜的人
Mostly innocent people.
只是认识我
Just knowing me is enough...
就会被里尔泽杀掉了
To get you killed by li'l z'.
-警方没有介入吗  -他们只抓我  不抓他
- The police don't go in there? - They go after me, not him.
我在牢里  而他还在肆无忌惮的杀人
I've been in jail, while he goes on killing undisturbed.
他们却没拘捕他
And they don't arrest him.
帅内德说争斗还将继续
Knockout ned says the war will continue.
警察局长盖蒂斯
Police chief Guedes
承诺一定会把两个帮派都逮捕归案
Has promised to arrest both of the gangs.
妈了个逼
Motherfucker!
我是这里的老大  报纸却登他的照片
I'm the boss here, but he gets his picture in the paper!
-上面有我没  -只有帅内德
- Have you found mine? - Just Knockout Ned's.
接着找
Keep looking.
里面至少会有我的大名
At least my name's got to be in there.
-啥也没有  -你认字吗
- There's nothing. - Can you read?
只认识照片
Just the pictures.
没有
Nothing.
你他妈的干毛呢
Hey, what the fuck are you doing?
上面只有招聘广告
It's just the want ads.
管他娘的  啥都给得我看
I don't care, read everything!
但是没有报道
But there aren't any articles.
脑袋想吃枪子吗
Want a bullet in your head?
让他们看看谁才是老大
Gotta show them who's boss here.
-相机给我  -没门
- Give me the camera! - No way!
给我拍个照片  小子
Take my picture, man.
我不会用
I can't work it.
拍拍看
Go ahead.
我要拿贝雷塔手枪
I'll hold the beretta.
我试下
Let me try.
一边去
Back off.
没有喀嚓声
There's no click.
一群蠢蛋
What a bunch of bozos!
跟你们一起  我就要玩完了
I'm fucked, with you guys.
有办法了
I have an idea.
我去找个哥们试试  别急
I'll go get a guy I know. Hang loose.
他来了
Here he is.
拿着相机
Take the camera.
好啊  小子
Well, kid?
你不是摄影师吗
Aren't you a photographer?
整整这个照相机  我们不会用
Make the camera work. We can't do it.
给哥几个照张相
Take our picture.
-你他妈的给整坏了  -不是我
- You fucking broke it. - It wasn't me.
我明白了
I found it.
一定是被撞了一下
It has to be wound.
你叫啥名
What's your name?
芝麻菜
Rocket.
再来一张  芝麻菜
Another picture, Rocket.
排成两排怎么样
How about two rows?
啥
What?
站两排  每个人都拿支枪
Two rows. Everyone with their guns.
你站到外面去了  怎么回事
You're outside, for christ's sake!
对他说话客气点  小子
Talk to him nicely, kid.
对不起  请站到里面来
Sorry. Move in, please.
再来一张
Another one.
我看胶卷拍完了
I think the roll's finished.
那把照片给我们看
Then show us the pictures.
还要冲洗一下
They have to be developed.
啥意思
Developed?
得多钱
How much is it?
拿着这钱
Take this money.
然后把照片拿来
And bring back the pictures.
那我要把胶卷取出来
I have to remove the film.
相机你就拿着吧
Keep the camera.
傻蛋原来不就是想给你吗
Benny wanted to give it to you, didn't he?
-是你的了  -谢谢
- It's yours. - Thanks.
别忘了拿照片回来
Don't forget the pictures.
照片  芝麻菜
The photos, Rocket!
-皮埃尔  -什么事
- Pierre! - What?
能把我这个洗一下吗
Can you develop this for me?
不行  芝麻菜  我会惹上麻烦的
I can't, Rocket. I could get into trouble.
只能给报社的记者冲洗  我不想丢掉工作
It's only for the paper's reporters. I could risk my job.
-皮埃尔  -什么事  罗杰里奥
- Pierre? - Yes, Rogerio?
把这些冲出来
Develop these for me.
这个也算里面  好吧
This one too, okay?
我吃午饭去了
I'm going to lunch.
你真走运  什么尺寸
You're lucky. What size?
啥
What?
要放大  洗多大的片
For the enlargement, what size?
你觉得最好就行了
Well... Whatever you think is best.
-这里 -谢谢
- Here. - Thanks.
大祸临头了
I'm in deep shit now.
我死定了
I'm as good as dead.
有人判处了我的死刑
Someone had signed my death sentence.
我真想把揍烂那个混蛋的脸
I wanted to bash the jerk's face in.
你是玛丽娜吗  你偷了我的照片
Are you Marina? You stole my photos.
就因为你  我要死了
Because of you, I'm dead.
什么死什么偷的  您什么意思
Dead? Stole? What do you mean?
不要这么大声
Not so loud.
还不要大声  因为你我就要死了
Not so loud? I'll be killed because of you.
你走了  照片就在冲洗室里
You were gone, your photos were in the lab.
我什么都没干
There's nothing I can do.
冲洗室的照片
The photos in our lab
都是要在报纸上刊登的
Are photos to be published in the paper.
我看见那些照片  我就登出来了
I saw the photos, I published them.
你偷了照片
You stole them.
我没有  就在这儿呢
I did not. Here they are.
-那把照片给我  -等等
- Give them to me. - Just a second.
这是你的照片
Here are your photos.
还有别的吗
Are there any others?
冷静  你叫什么名字
Calm down. What's your name?
-芝麻菜  -芝麻菜?
- Rocket. - Rocket?
幸会  我是玛丽娜
Nice to meet you. I'm Marina.
别激动  我给你钱
Now, relax. I have money for you.
作为照片的报酬
For your pictures.
当报社选登了某张照片
Here, when we use a picture
我们会付给摄影师报酬
We pay the photographer.
你想当摄影师吗
Do you want to be a photographer?
是的
Yes.
开端不错  头版头条
Great start! On the front page.
你是怎么拍到这些片子的
How'd you get these photos?
我住在那里
I live there.
芝麻菜  从来没有摄影师住在那里面
Rocket, no photographer has ever been able to go in there.
如果你能拍到更多里尔泽的片子
If you could bring us more pictures of Li'lz',
报社就全部买下
The paper would buy them.
我们付给你报酬
We'd pay you.
愿意吗
Could you?
我不知道
I don't know.
有什么问题吗
What's the problem?
问题  问题就是我晚上再也不能出门了
The problem? I can't go there anymore at night.
那白天呢
And during the day?
太危险了
It's too risky.
瞧瞧  他们终于知道谁是这里的老大了
Look, man! They've finally understood that I'm the boss.
你那个摄影的朋友叫啥来着
What's your photographer-friend's name?
芝麻菜
Rocket.
这家伙不错  我还要拍更多的片
He's good. I'll take more to show the others.
芝麻菜  愿意还是不愿意
So, Rocket, is it yes or no?
这机会可是千载难逢啊
It's a great opportunity.
好吧
Okay.
你的决定是对的
You made the right choice.
非常好
Very good!
我会给你一些胶卷  镜头
I'll give you some film, lenses,
甚至另一部相机  我带你看下设备间
And even another camera. I'll show you the equipment room.
还有个问题
There's another problem.
-什么  -今晚上我睡哪儿啊
- What is it? - Where can I sleep tonight?
现在我回不去了
I can't go back now.
这是135mm的
This is a 135mm.
想拍近景还是远景
Will you be close up or far away?
远的
Far away.
-会控光吗  -恩
- Can you measure the light? - Yes.
你是不是太近了
Aren't you too close?
我不知道哪来的勇气跟他们那么说话
I don't know what spurred me to go talk to them like that.
也许我就要死了
Maybe I was going to die,
不过现在我得到了一个相机
But now I had a camera
还有成为摄影师的机会
And a chance to become a photographer.
注意脚下的狗屎
Watch out for the dog shit.
而且夜色尚早
Not to mention that the night was still young.
想吃点什么吗
Want something to eat?
不谢谢  女士
No, thank you, ma'am.
什么也不吃  什么也不喝
Nothing to eat? Nothing to drink?
吸大麻吗
A joint?
试试这个
Try this.
该睡觉了
It's time to go to sleep.
我带你看下床
I'll show you your bed.
你有热水吧
You have hot water, don't you?
恩  你从没洗过热水淋浴吗
Yes. You've never taken a hot shower?
-没  -那你们怎么洗的
- No. - What do you do?
我们烧热水
We heat up the kettle.
你为什么还站在那儿
Why are you standing there?
我睡哪个房间
What room do I sleep in?
真遗憾  只有一个房间
Unfortunately, there's only one room.
你得跟我睡在一起
You have to sleep with me.
我不想详细介绍我的第一次性经验
I won't go into the details of my first sexual experience.
只是放松一下
Just relax.
因为  另一个地方
Because, elsewhere
一场关乎贫民窟的重要的性事
Another more important sex scene for the slum
正在上演
Was taking place.
就在看守帅内德警察
Carrot was helping Knockout Ned escape
和护士干得大汗淋漓的时候
Without firing a shot.
萝卜不声不响的
The policeman guarding him
把他救了出来
Was in the willing hands of the nurse.
与此同时
And in the meantime
为了铲除萝卜  里尔泽正在买进军火
To eliminate Carrot,  Li'lz'was investing in munitions.
他买进了一大笔  即使没钱付
He invested heavily, even if he couldn't pay.
双管枪记得不
Remember the double-barrel?
已经搞到手了
I already have it.
这是来福枪
This is a repeater rifle.
你们没有这个  伯朗宁自动手枪
You don't have this one, the browning.
用它都能打下一架飞机
It'll shoot down a plane.
我打飞机干屁  我要的那种呢
I'm not shooting down planes. And the one I asked for?
Ar-15  美国佬
The Ar-15, uncle sam.
巴西搞不到那个
You can't get them in brazil.
操  美国佬
My ass, uncle sam.
我想到办法了
I have a solution.
罗格  见过没
The rugger. Ever seen one?
很像Ar-15  口径相同  重量轻一些
It's like the ar-15. Same caliber, but lighter.
带红外瞄准具吗  每分能连发400的吗
With an infrared sight? 400 shots a minute?
那要看情况
It depends.
看鸡毛情况
It depends, my ass!
耍我吗
Trying to fuck me over?
我先操你大爷的
I'll fuck you over first.
赶紧滚蛋  钱和枪都不准拿
You leave now without the money or the guns.
那我怎么和老板交代
What do I tell the boss?
那是你的事
That's your problem.
你会想出办法的
You'll think of something.
听见没  滚蛋
You heard him, chubby? Get out.
逃吧  胖子
Beat it, fatso.
里尔泽犯了一个大错
Li'lz' had made a big mistake.
他应该知道
He should have known
每个推销员身后都有一个供应商
That behind every salesman lies a supplier.
他们可从不开玩笑
And they don't joke around.
看见这个没有
Have you seen this?
他们要Ar-15干什么
What do they need an Ar-15 for?
这会牵扯警方进来调查
These stories will push the police to investigate.
他们会抓住你  还有我  和你一起
They'll nab you. And me, along with you.
你觉得我会把你供出来吗
Think I'm going to give you away?
别担心  这事我会处理好的
Don't worry, i'll take care of it.
但是别再瞎搞了
But don't fuck up again.
查理
Charlie!
过来
Come here!
听着
Listen,
你告诉他
You tell him.
就让这个推销员的贱命来抵账吧
Let's go make that sleaze little dealer pay up.
过来  小伙子们
Come here, kids!
喜欢吃鸡不
Do you like chicken?
那要看怎么做
It depends.
一会儿我们吃鸡
We'll eat some chicken
然后把萝卜做成点心
And have Carrot for dessert.
我有一个礼物给你们
I have a present for you.
这里
Here.
给你们的一份大礼
A big one for you.
你真的要把这些枪都给我们吗
Are you really giving us these guns?
对  但你们要站在我这边  对抗萝卜
Yes, but I want you on my side, against Carrot.
我们也可以抢劫任何人吗
Then can we hold up anyone we want?
不是这儿的就行
Not in the slum.
-会开枪吗  -马马虎虎吧
- Can you shoot? - More or less.
啥叫马马虎虎
More or less?
你们几个  来帮帮这几个小鬼
Hey, you guys, come help these kids.
我知道  你们是这么弄得
I know. You do it like this.
末日的先兆
抓住那只鸡
Get that chicken!
来啊  追啊
C'mon, let's go.
如果被里尔泽抓住了  他会杀了你的
If Li'lz' catches you, he'll kill you.
那也得看看他能不能找到我
Yeah, well, he's gotta find me first.
小鬼  抓住那只鸡
Hey, kid! Get that chicken!
操  条子来了
Shit! The cops!
跑你妈个毛啊
Hell, don't fucking run off!
把枪给我
Give me that.
傻瓜  说你呢  跑腿的
Hey, melonhead! You fucking fag!
赶快滚蛋
Get the hell out of here!
胆小鬼
Coward!
蠢货
Asshole!
走吧  让他们自相残杀
Come on, let them kill each other.
他们能自己了结的
They can fuck themselves.
芝麻菜  给哥几个拍张片
Rocket! Take a picture of us!
还磨蹭啥呢
What are you waiting for?
怎么了
What's happening?
操
Shit!
撤
Let's go!
快跑
Run! Run!
小心
Watch out!
杀了哪个都行啊  炸死他
Kill one of these faggots! Blast him!
帅内德
Knockout Ned!
放松  别动
Take it easy. Don't move.
哥们  我受伤了
It hurts, man.
放松一点就好了  小鬼
Easy does it, kid.
你为啥也进来火拼
Why did you join this fucking war?
帅内德
Knockout Ned!
里尔泽撞车了  来啊
Li'lz's been hit. Come on!
在这等着  我一会儿救你
Wait here, i'll help you.
坚持住
Just hold on.
-你叫什么  -奥托
- What's your name? - My name's Otto.
我要为父报仇
I want to get my father's murderer.
帅内德  里尔泽撞车了  来啊
Knockout Ned! Li'lz's been hit. Come on!
我会救你的
I'll help you.
在这坚持住
Just hold on there.
又是他妈的条子
The fucking cops!
趴在地上
On the ground!
-不准动  -双手举过头顶
- Don't move! - Hands over your head.
-我要找的就是你  -你完了  老兄
- You're the one I want. - You're finished, pal.
铐上他
Handcuff him.
芝麻菜  你要去哪儿
Rocket, where are you going?
我要查清楚一些事
I got something to clear up.
好了  冤家
Okay, lovebirds.
来吧  里尔泽  算算咱们的帐
Come on, Li'lz', let's go settle our scores.
没你的事  你是交给媒体的礼物
Not you. You're a present for the media.
这就够1万了吧
Does it come to 10,000?
差不多  我全身上下就这些
Almost. That's all I have.
都在这  警官
That's all there was, chief.
每个地方都搜查过了
We searched everywhere.
放了他
Let him go.
这戒指是金子的吗
What about this ring? Is it gold?
先把这些填上  剩下的算是你欠我们的
Fill it up. You'll owe us the rest.
拼你妈了个逼
Fucking war!
帅内德挂了  我也身无分文
Knockout Ned is dead and I'm dead broke!
玩完了吧
You're fucked, eh?
小鬼们
Kids,
我们要多抢几次  东山再起
We'll have to do a few hold-ups to get my business going again.
东山再起  里尔泽
Your business, Li'lz'?
咋回事  小鬼
What's your problem, kid?
这是为我们朋友的  混蛋
This is for our friend, motherfucker!
苏维埃起义
A soviet attack!
天下是我们的啦
The business is ours!
这片子让我得到衣食无忧的工作
This picture of the hood will guarantee my salary.
会让我出名
This one will make me famous.
甚至可能登上杂志封面
It'll even make the cover of a magazine.
我再也不用担心里尔泽了
I won't have to worry about Li'lz' anymore.
可还有警察呢
But the cops?
匪首  自诩为上帝之城的主宰  中弹身亡
Gangster, self-styled ''boss'' of the city of god, shot dead
这片子也许会给我们带来杀身横祸
This photo could've gotten us killed?
我想是这样
I think so.
至少它给了你一份工作
A least it got you a job.
不是工作  只是实习
Not a job, an internship.
薪水多吗
It pays a little, doesn't it?
一点点
A little.
那个女记者呢  是个不错的女伴吗
What about that lady journalist? Was she a good lay?
凑合吧
More or less.
你不喜欢吗
You didn't like it?
我觉得做记者的床上功夫不咋地
I don't think journalists know how to screw.
我猜也是
Yeah, I Guess so.
可可在巴拉连抢了3家
Cocoa robbed 3 houses in barra.
最好灭了他
Better kill him.
罗格是谁干掉的
Who shot Roger?
-牛肉  -杀了那贱人
- It was beef. - Kill that fucker.
我们还要杀了警察和鬼佬
We should kill the chief and gringo as well.
雪莉怎么办
What about cherry?
走  咱俩  还有3个
Let's go. Us two, and 3 others.
就这么办
It's a deal.
你听说过赤军吗
Have you heard of the red brigade?
没有  他们敢来  我们就灭了他们
No, but if they come, we'll kill them.
-谁会写字  -我  会一点儿
- Who knows how to write? - Me, sort of.
咱们先列一个黑名单  然后全部杀光
Let's make a black list. We'll kill them all.
把夜鹰列上
Put fucking nightowl on there.
还有棒槌
And Croquet.
填上伦纳德  他欠我钱
Leonard, too, he owes me money.
还有支那男  他自以为了不起
And china-man, he thinks he's hot stuff.
还有爆眼人
And claudio.
吉安特在哪儿呢
Where's giant?
跟上  吉安特
Come on, giant!
我忘说了
I forgot to say,
我不叫芝麻菜了
My name isn't Rocket anymore.
现在的我是摄影师威尔森・罗德里格斯
I'm now wilson rodriGues, photographer.
曼纽尔・马查多  又称帅内德
Manuel machado, aka Knockout Ned,
被里尔泽帮枪伤之后被送往医院
Was hospitalized after being wounded by Li'lz's gang.
出院的时候  本报的记者采访了他
On leaving the hospital, our reporter interviewed him.
很多人死了  大多数都是无辜的人
Many have died. Mostly innocent people.
有的只是知道我
Just knowing me is enough,
只是我朋友
Just being my friend.
他要是觉得谁认识我
If he thinks someone knows me,
就会杀光他们
He'll kill them.
警方没介入吗
The police don't go in there?
他们只抓我  而不是他
They go after me, not him.
我已经蹲了3次监狱了
I've been in jail 3 times, while he goes on
而他还在滥杀无辜
Killing undisturbed.
警方也不逮捕他
And they don't arrest him.
帅内德说火拼仍将继续
Knockout Ned says the war will continue.
警察局长盖蒂斯承诺
Police chief Guedes has promised to arrest
一定会把两个帮派都逮捕归案
Both gangs in the city of god.